# **BOB WEEK**

Computational Biologist

#### SUMMARY

I am interested in applying my background in mathematical and computational methods to solve difficult problems faced by industry. My experience makes me uniquely positioned to develop and analyze simulations and models used to optimize industrial processes.

🔇 bobweek.github.io 🔽 bweek.ecoevo@proton.me

**\** 360 216 9074 **(7)** github.com/bobweek

SKILLS

Software:

Julia, Python, R, Linux, Mathematica,

SLURM, C/C++, Matlab

Math: Linear Algebra, Dynamical Systems,

Harmonic Analysis, Stochastic Processes

**Statistics:** Modeling, Analysis, Inference

(e.g., GLM, PCA, MCMC, KDE, ABC, GRF)

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## 2022 - Current Postdoctoral Research Fellow

#### B.J.M. Bohannan Lab, University of Oregon

- · Developed a novel mathematical framework to understand microbiome-mediated host evolution
  - · This is the first time such a genralization has been formally carried out
    - $\cdot \ \, \text{Conceptually novel approach formally generalizing biological inheritance using path analysis}$
- · Developed individual-based simulations to test the mathematical framework
  - $\cdot$  Chose Julia for fast implementation, JIT-compilation, and ease of parallelization
- · Implented multi-threading on a computational cluster in Julia to compare theory and simulations
  - · Multi-threading was necessary to overcome time constraints
- Mathematical framework and associated simulation model are under review at The Royal Society B
  - · Code for the simulation model is available at github.com/bobweek/host-microbe-sims
- · Developed a novel genetically-explicit spatial host-microbe simulation model in Julia
  - · The model is novel due to including explicit genome evolution and host spatial structure
  - · Chose Julia for fast implementation, JIT-compilation, and ease of parallelization
  - · Used sparse matrices for representing genomic data to improve simulation performance
  - · Code for this simulation model is available at github.com/bobweek/spatial-genetic-host-microbe

## 2020 - 2022 Postdoctoral Researcher

#### G. Bradburd Lab, Michigan State University

- · Developed an individual-based model of spatial host-parasite coevolution
  - · Implemented this model using the SLiM simulation framework (messerlab.org/slim)
    - · Used this model to derive an SPDE model and analytical results using Fourier analysis
- · Applied SVD (singular value decomposition) to simulate multivariate Gaussian fields in Julia
  - $\cdot$  This provided a numerical method to sample equilibrium solutions of the SPDE model
  - Chose SVD instead of Cholesky because high numerical stability was required
    Chose Julia because of fast implementation
- The SPDE model is published at doi.org/10.1086/727470
- Used SLURM to schedule large-scale simulations on a High-Performance Computing Cluster
- · Applied FFT in NumPy to analyze coherence of simulated genomic data
  - · Chose this approach to identify the spatial signature of coevolution on genomic data
  - · Chose NumPy because Python also has tools for efficient analysis of genomic data
- Code for the simulation model is available at github.com/bobweek/genomic-sign-coev-cont-sp

### 2015 - 2020 Doctoral Student

#### S.L. Nuismer Lab, University of Idaho

- Developed heuristics to calculate population-level models from individual-based models
  - $\cdot$  This is useful for analyzing simulations and deriving mechanistic analytical models
- Developed heuristics using infinite-dimensional stochastic analysis to calculate SDE from SPDE
- · Applied the above heuristics to generalize existing eco-evolutionary mathematical frameworks
  - · This framework is published at doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2021.110660
- · Developed numerical methods to solve associated SPDE and simulate rescaled processes
  - · Associated code is available at github.com/bobweek/white.noise.community.ecology
- · Developed a model-based maximum likelihood method to measure species coevolution
  - · This required developing a model of coevolution yielding a tractable likelihood function
  - $\cdot\,$  Implemented this method in R to make it accessible for empirical biologists
  - · This project is published at doi.org/10.1111/ele.13231
- Modeled the coevolutionary maintence of mutualism, published at doi.org/10.1086/714274

SELECTED PROJECTS ————————————————————————————————————			
2023	he Evolution of Microbiome-Mediated Traits github.com/bobweek/host-microbe-sims nalytical and simulation models of host trait evolution mediated by microbiome transmission		
2023	Host-Parasite Coevolution in Continuous Space zenodo.org/ A stochastic partial differential equation model for spatial analysis of host-parasite coevolu	zenodo.org/records/8008017 lysis of host-parasite coevolution	
2022	The Genomic Signature of Coevolution github.com/bobweek/genomic-substitution of coevolution and spatial analysis of simulated genomic data	b.com/bobweek/genomic-sign-coev-cont-sp simulated genomic data	
2021	White Noise Evolutionary Ecology An application of infinite-dimensional stochastic calculus to unify eco-evolutionary models		
2019	Measuring Coevolution github.com/bobweek/meas A maximum likelihood method to measure coevolution using spatial trait data	suring.coevolution	
EDUCATION —			
2020	PhD Bioinformatics & Computational Biology S.L. Nuismer Lab, Unissertation focused on modeling eco-evolutionary processes and developing statistical in		
2015	<b>BS Mathematics</b> Traditional math degree with electives Digital Logic, Signals & Systems, Physics, and Numerous Company (1997).	<b>University of Idaho</b> erical Methods	
AWARDS -			
2018 - 2019	Bioinformatics & Computational Biology Fellowship  Project aimed to model the duration of coevolutionary associations	University of Idaho	
2017-2018	Bioinformatics & Computational Biology Fellowship  Project aimed to develop a method to measure coevolution in continuous space	University of Idaho	
2017	Paul Joyce Memorial BCB Fellowship Endowment  Nominated by Professor Scott Nuismer because of my "love for mathematics and helping preciate how it can be used to understand biological processes"	<b>University of Idaho</b> g others to ap-	
2013-2015	Undergraduate Research in Biology & Mathematics  Efforts focused on developing a method to measure coevolution in discrete space	University of Idaho	